Finding Aid for Church of the Holy Spirit (Livonia, Mich.) records, 1969-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Church of the Holy Spirit (Livonia, Mich.) records 1969-2011
Church of the Holy Spirit (Livonia, Mich.)
5 linear feet
2012176 Ba 2
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from the Episcopal Church, Diocese of Michigan (donor no. 1059 ) and came to the library in 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The idea that an Episcopal mission should be founded to serve southwest Livonia and the adjacent areas began in 1964 when Bishop Richard S. Emrich asked the people of St. Andrew's, Livonia, to obtain property for that purpose. A ten-acre site on Newburgh Road just north of Joy Road was purchased in July 1964.
Early in 1968, a committee was formed at St. Andrew's from among families living in the southwest section of Livonia. Concerned about the nature of their "mission," members of these families were apprehensive about acquiring a physical plant which would absorb a significant portion of their resources at the expense of missionary efforts and service to the community. The committee made the decision not to build.
The first service was held in July 1969 after the decision was made to share the building owned by All Saints Lutheran Church at Newburgh and Joy Roads. A year later the growth of the mission made sharing no longer practical and a building owned by the Merriman Road Baptist Church located on Cowan Road near Wayne Road in Westland was leased. It was home for the congregation for the next nine years. Concerns about the need to be located in Livonia made it necessary to reconsider constructing a church building. With the support of the Diocese, a new building was erected on the Newburgh property. Services began there the third Sunday of Easter, 1980. The building was dedicated September 21, 1980.
The Community Outreach program ranked of highest importance next to worship. Based on what is referred to as the "Virginia Plan," which advocates dedicating fifty percent of a parish's resources toward the support of community projects, this program was funded from the Mission budget and augmented with the time and talent of members. Other projects included CESA, Crossroads, Mariners' Inn, First Step, St. Christopher's House, Campus Crusade for Christ, St. Peter's Church -- COTS, Special Ministry for Epilepsy, Hospice, and the Presiding Bishop's Fund.
Like several other Episcopal churches and missions in the Detroit metropolitan area, the Church of the Holy Spirit lost membership in the 1990s and into the new century. The last service of the church was May 11, 2011.
The records of the Church of the Holy Spirit have been arranged into the following series: Registers of baptisms, communicants, burials, marriages, etc.; Registers of church services; Bishop's Committee; Reports; Bulletins and newsletters; Miscellaneous; and Membership records.
Subjects:
Church of the Holy Spirit (Livonia, Mich.); Episcopal Church--Michigan--Livonia.; Livonia (Mich.)--Church history.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Livonia.
- Registers of baptisms, communicants, burials, marriages, etc.
  - 1969-1972 (Box 1)
    (some record of marriages date from 1980s up to 2001)
  - 1972-1985 (Box 1)
  - 1985-1991 (Box 1)
    (include some later dates)
  - 1992-2001 (Box 1)
  - 2002-2011 (Box 1)
- Church registers
  - 1969-2011, 4 volumes (Box 1)
- Bishop's Committee
  - Minutes and other materials
    - 1995-2001, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 2002-2011, 10 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Reports
  - Annual reports to members, 1970-2011, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Parochial reports to the diocese, 1980-2010 (scattered), 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Parish Statistical Reports (covering multiple years, 1992-2002, 1994-1998 1995-1999) (Box 2)
  - Racial and ethnic heritage report, 1998 (Box 2)
- Bulletins and newsletters
  - Newsletter, 2001-2011, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Mission Cycle of Prayer, 2004-2006 (Box 3)
  - Bulletins from services, 2005-2011, 7 folders (Box 3)
  - Funeral bulletins, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  - Program: A Celebration of the Life and Ministry of Church of the Holy Spirit, Livonia, Michigan (Box 3)
  - Portraits of clergy (Box 3)
- Membership records
  - Baptism applications (Box 4)
  - Confirmation applications (Box 4)
  - Family records, A-Z, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Funeral and burial forms (Box 4)
  - Transfer In, applications, A-Z, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Transfer Out, A-Z, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Wedding applications (Box 4)
  - Directories, 1970-2011, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Card files with membership information (Box 5)
    (some of the files provide indexes to the registers of baptisms, etc.)